<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>CZT subprojects</title> 
  </header> 
  <body>
    <p>
      The CZT project consists of the following subprojects:
    </p>

    <section id="zml">
      <title><link href="site:zml">ZML</link></title>
      <p>
        <link href="site:zml">ZML</link>
        defines an XML markup for Z specifications.
      </p>
      <p>
        Most of the other subprojects depend directly or indirectly
        on this subproject since the AST Java classes in
        <link href="#corejava">Corejava</link>
        are generated from the ZML Schema using the code generator
        <link href="#gnast">GnAST</link>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="corejava">
      <title><link href="ext:corejava">Corejava</link></title>
      <p>
        <link href="ext:corejava">Corejava</link>
        contains AST (Annotated Syntax Tree) classes for standard Z,
        Object Z, and TCOZ written in Java.  It is closely related to
        <link href="#zml">ZML</link> since most of
        the classes and interfaces in this subproject
        are automatically generated
        from the XML Schema using the code generator
        <link href="#gnast">GnAST</link>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="gaffe">
      <title>Gaffe</title>
      <p>
        This is a GUI builder for Z animators.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="gnast">
      <title>GnAST</title>
      <p>
        This is a code generator that generates Java interfaces and classes
        (for instance, the AST in
        <link href="#corejava">Corejava</link>)
        from an XML Schema.
      </p>
      <p>
        Note that GnAST is not (yet) designed to be released.
        It is used internally by CZT developers to generate code for
        other subprojects of CZT.  However, the source code is available
        via <link href="ext:cztcvsinfo">CVS</link>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="jedit">
      <title>JEdit plugins</title>
      <p>
        This is a collection of tools, modes and plugins for the
        <link href="ext:jedit">JEdit editor</link>
        which provide support for editing Z specifications.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="parser">
      <title><link href="ext:parser">Parser</link></title>
      <p>
        <link href="ext:parser">Parser</link>
        contains parser and printer utilities for standard and Object Z
        specifications written in unicode or using latex markup.
        Support for e-mail markup as well as TCOZ is planned.
        The output of the parser is an AST (see
        <link href="#corejava">Corejava</link>)
        and can be written as an XML file, using the <link href="#zml">ZML
        format</link>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="zlive">
      <title>ZLive</title>
      <p>This is an animator for Z.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="zmltp">
      <title>ZMLTP</title>
      <p>
        This is a
        <link href="#zml">ZML</link> to HTML transformer.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
