<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v13.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>CZT User Manual</title> 
  </header> 
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>About CZT</title>
      <p>
        The Community Z Tools (CZT) project is a set of tools for
        editing, typechecking and animating formal specifications
        written in the Z specification language.
      </p>
      <p>
        For historical reasons, there are two bundles on the sourceforge
        web-site.  The bundle "corejava" is deprecated and contains
        only old releases of corejava.  The bundle "czt" is a collection
        of tools like parser and typechecker, and also contains "corejava".
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Source Releases</title>
      <p>
        This manual assumes you want to install czt_0_3.
        <link href="installation.html">Here</link> are installation
        instructions for the older czt releases czt_0_1 and czt_0_2.
      </p>
      <section>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>
        <p>
          You need at least
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <link href="site:jdk">
              Java 2 SDK 1.5 or higher
            </link>
          </li>
          <li>
            <link href="site:ant">Ant 1.6 or higher</link>
          </li>
          <li>
            <link href="site:beanshell">BeanShell</link>
          </li>
          <li>
            <link href="site:jflex">
              JFlex 1.4.1 or higher
            </link>
          </li>
          <li>
            <link href="site:jwsdp">
              JWSDP 1.5 or higher
            </link>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          to build and run CZT.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you don't have one of these installed on your system,
          you must download and install it to compile and run the software.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section id="building">
        <title>Building the sources</title>
        <p>
          Download the CZT source release from
          <link href="site:development">Sourceforge</link>,
          unpack it and change into the installation directory.
        </p>
        <p>
          Customise the file
          <code>czt.properties</code>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Run
          <code>ant</code>.
          By default, ant will build the jar files and install them in the
          <code>&lt;CZT_HOME&gt;/lib</code>
          directory.  Optionally, you can pass an
          argument to ant.  Call
          <code>ant -projecthelp</code>
          to get help information about which arguments are available.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you have trouble compiling, please read the
          <code>README.txt</code>
          file within the sub-project you have trouble with.
          If this does not help, report a bug or file a support request at our
          <link href="site:development">sourceforge web-site</link>.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sources from CVS</title>
      <p>
        If you are really feeling adventurous, you can try to build
        CZT using the sources from CVS.  See the
        <link href="site:cztcvsinfo">
          documentation about CVS on sourceforge
        </link>
        for more information about how to access the CZT repository.
      </p>
      <p>
        Starting from 3 June 2005, the corejava AST classes are no
        no longer in the CVS repository but must be generated using
        the code generator gnast, which is included in the CVS
        repository.  The same applies to the JAXB generated classes.
        This requires that, in addition to the software mentioned
        above, you will need to install
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <link href="site:velocity">Velocity 1.4</link>
        </li>
        <li>
          <link href="site:xalan">XalanJ 2.5.0</link>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        and customise the file
        <code>czt.properties</code>
        appropriately to build CZT from source.
      </p>
      <p>
        Now you can compile the sources as described
        <link href="#building">above</link>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing the CZT jEdit plugin</title>
      <p>
        First make sure jEdit is really using Java 1.5,
	you can do that by clicking on
	"Macros / Properties / System Properties" and checking that
	property java.version is set to 1.5, and deinstall the old CZT
	plugin if necessary.
      </p>
      <p>
        Since the plugin is installed manually (not using the plugin manager),
        we also need to take care of the plugin's dependencies.  The ErrorList
        plugin is required by the CZT plugin, so please install the "ErrorList"
        plugin from within jEdit's plugin manager, and then use the 
        "Plugins / ErrorList / Error List" menu entry to start up the
        ErrorList plugin.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you plan to view or edit Z specifications in Unicode markup,
        you should  also install the jEdit "Whitespace" plugin and enable the
        "Show other whitespaces" option (use the "Plugins / WhiteSpaces" menu),
        to ensure that you can see the ENDZED character.
      </p>

      <p>
        Now copy all the necessary jar files (these are all jar files
        provided by the binary release EXCEPT bsh.jar, or all jar files
        in the directory plugin.jar.dir set in the czt.properties file in
        case of a source release).
        to the /jars subdirectory of either:
        (a) the directory in which jEdit is installed, or
        (b) your user settings directory (which you can find
        by evaluating the BeanShell expression
        "jEdit.getSettingsDirectory()";
	select "Utilities / BeanShell / Evaluate BeanShell Expression").
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using the CZT jEdit plugin</title>
      <p>
        After you restart jEdit, you should now find an entry
        "Community Z Tools"
        in the plugin menu, which pops up the CZT plugin.  It will show some
        "missing font" square boxes until you install the CZT font (below).
        We like to "dock" this plugin at the top or bottom of the main jEdit 
        window -- see the jEdit documentation how plugins can be docked etc.
      </p>

      <p>
        Documentation for the CZT plugin can be viewed via the
        "Help / jEdit Help"
        menu, then scroll down to the "Plugins / Community Z Tools" entry.
      </p>

      <p>
        You can test the installation so far by opening the sample bbook.zed
        specification and typechecking it (click the "Typecheck" button in the
        CZT plugin).  After a few seconds, it should say 
        "Z typechecking complete, 0 errors" at the bottom of the CZT plugin.
        You might like to try inserting some syntax errors, to see how they are
        reported using the ErrorList plugin (Note: you must open the ErrorList
        plugin to see the errors, then you can click on an error to go the
        the cause of the problem in the Z specification).
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing the CZT font</title>
      <p>
        We are not experts in installing fonts, so please check the
        documentation of your operating system how fonts are installed.  The
        following summarises our experiences with installing the font on
        Windows XP and Linux.
      </p>

      <section>
        <title>Installing the CZT font on Windows XP</title>
        <p>
          Go into Start/Control Panel, then into the "Fonts" program.
          (If you are using the new XP categories, you need to select
          "Appearance and Themes" first, then the "Fonts" link will appear
          in the left-hand sidebar).  Once you are in the "Fonts" program,
          use the "File/Install new font" menu entry, then browse to the
          fonts/ttf subdirectory  and add the "CZT Sans" font.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Installing the CZT font on Linux</title>
        <p>
          Executing the following commands worked for me on gentoo
          (without having root privileges):
        </p>
        <source>
          cd fonts/ttf
          ttmkfdir > fonts.scale
          mkfontdir
          xset fp+ `pwd`
          xset fp rehash
        </source>

        <p>
          More information can be obtained from:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><link href="site:gnomefonts">The Gnome Web-Site</link></li>
          <li><link href="site:font-howto">The Font HOWTO</link></li>
          <li><link href="site:ttfonts">The Malta Linux User Group</link></li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Selecting the CZT font within jEdit</title>
        <p>
          After installing the font, we must tell jEdit to use that font
          in all its buffers.  To do this, go into the jEdit global settings
          panel (you can use the "Utilities / Global Options" menu to open
          this panel), then into the "Text Area" pane and set the "Text Font"
          to be CZT (clicking on the existing font name will open a requestor,
          then you can scroll down the left-hand column to select the "CZT"
          family). You might also like to enable the "Smooth Text" and
          "Fractional Font Metrics" on this "Text Area" pane, to turn on
          anti-aliasing of fonts.
        </p>

        <p>
          You need to restart jEdit to see the font in the CZT plugin as well,
          since the font in the CZT plugin cannot yet be set dynamically.  
          After you have done this, you should see all the Z characters
          in the CZT plugin (no little square boxes, which mean a missing
          symbol in the font).  
        </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Test it -- create a Z Unicode specification!</title>
        <p>
          In jEdit, use the "File / New" menu entry to create a new file.
          Then select "Unicode Markup" in the CZT plugin.
          Then click the "Sect",  "::=" and "Sch" buttons in the CZT plugin.
          These should insert a section header, then a free type definition,
          then a schema definition.  The resulting buffer should look like the
          example screenshot.png in this directory.  If you are missing some
          of the Z symbols, then recheck the CZT font installation.
          If you cannot see the ENDZED characters (the little red diamonds),
          then make sure you have installed the "WhiteSpace" plugin and
          turned on the "Show other whitespace" option.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Running CZT without jEdit</title>
      <p>
        Another way to explore CZT is to use the
        <link href="site:beanshell">beanshell</link>
        console and try the various CZT commands provided in
        <code>CZT_HOME/bin/bsh</code>.  To do this just install
        CZT and call the script <code>beanshell</code> which is
        located in <code>CZT_HOME/bin</code>.  You should now
        get a beanshell console window, where you can type your
        commands.  Make sure to call
        <code>importCommands("bsh");</code> to get access to the
        CZT commands.
     </p>
     <p>
       An examples session could look like this (please substitute
       CZT_HOME with your CZT home directory):
     </p>
     <source>
       BeanShell
       2.0b1.1 - by Pat Niemeyer (pat@pat.net)
       bsh % importCommands("bsh");
       bsh % cd("CZT_HOME/examples/z");
       bsh % term = unmarshal("eg1.xml"); // unmarshal an example file
       bsh % print(term); // print the root of the AST
       net.sourceforge.czt.z.impl.SpecImpl@a15dfd30
       bsh % print(term.getVersion());  // show the version of the Spec
       1.1
       bsh % print(toLatex(term)); // transform the AST to LaTex
       \begin{zed} ...
     </source>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
