<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>ZLive Release Notes</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <release version="1.0" date="July 2007">
      <action dev="open" type="add">
         The calculation of free/bound variables now handles tmpNNN
         variables as normal variables, so that they are scoped correctly.
         This was necessary to avoid errors in the mode calculations, such
         as for sets whose results contained tmpNNN variables.
      </action>
      <action dev="open" type="add">
        Implemented a FlatPred implementation of function/relation types,
        like in Jaza.  That is, an implementation of A --> B, for all 
        the kinds of functions/relations/sequences that Z supports.
        (Use flags to keep track of each property such as one-to-one,
        total, onto etc.)
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU, Petra" type="update">
        Separated the FlatPred hierarchy from the evaluated results that it
        returns (see the net.sourceforge.czt.animation.eval.result package).
        For example, FlatPowerSet now returns a PowerSet object each time
        it is evaluated.  This is more flexible, and was necessary to handle
        examples like {a:1..10 @ \power(0..a)}.
      </action>
      <action dev="Petra, MarkU" type="add">
       	Implemented a better mode algorithm to reorder lists of FlatPreds,
       	based on the estimated number of solutions for each mode.
        Initially, just repeatedly choose the predicate with the 
        smallest number of expected solutions.  In the future, more 
        sophisticated path-finding algorithms may be used, such as 
        best-first or A* path-finding algorithms.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5" date="July 6, 2006">
      <action dev="Mark" type="fix">
      	Fix flatpred/FlatForall.java so that simple bounded forall predicates
        work.  For example: (\forall x:\{1,3,5\} @ x = 3) should be false,
        but currently gives a "Cannot find mode" error.  
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
      	Design and implement a bounds analysis feature for numeric variables,
      	so that x&lt;=10 and x&gt;=y are combined
      	into the (finite) constraint x \in y..10.
      	This could be done in at least three ways: (1) associate
      	a static lower and upper bound constant with each variable; 
      	(2) associate a set of lower/upper bound expressions with each
      	variable; (3) merge several complementary FlatPred constraints into
      	single FlatPred constraint which is more efficient.  The first or
      	third approaches seem more in keeping with the ZLive philosophy
      	of static analysis/transformation.
      </action>
      <action context="tests" dev="MarkU" type="fix">
      	Change the test-and-compare framework so that a single directory
        is used for the results (and these change with time).
	This is a more CVS-friendly way of recording our progress.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
	Implement set union as a new FlatPred subclass.  This should give us
        more flexibility to choose different algorithms than just unfolding the
        definition of union, which is a set comprehension with a disjunction.
        Intersection and difference might be okay done via unfolding.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
      	Unfold definitions and rewrite some complex constructs into
      	simpler constructs.  This will be done via CZT rules.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="update">
        Change the FlatSetComp implementation of sets so that members
	are generated lazily, on demand.  This will allow us to evaluate
	schemas that have an infinite number of solutions, when we only
	want to explore the first few solutions.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
      	Design and implement a 'FlatOr' class to handle disjunctions.
      	All branches of the disjunct must have the same mode. 
      	Other complex predicates should probably be unfolded into disjunctions.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
      	Implemented a simple textual user interface which provides
        eval Expr and evalp Pred commands.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1" date="unreleased">
      <action dev="Rohit" type="add">
      	Better reporting from the usertests.  Each animate*.tex file
      	is a separate JUnit test suite so that we can see which groups
      	of tests are mostly passing/failing.  It shows line numbers for each
      	test that fails and records previous test runs in subdirectories
	and shows when new tests pass or old tests start failing.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU, Rohit" type="add">
        Implemented all basic arithmetic operators, tuples and several 
        implementations of sets.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU, Rohit" type="add">
        Designed the EvalSet interface.  Rohit wrote the first implementation
        of it (RangeSet for a..b sets), plus the FlatMember predicate
        which uses it.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU" type="add">
        Designed basic architecture of ZLive (unfolding, flattening, 
        mode analysis, reordering, then evaluation), and the FlatPred
        interface (abstract class actually).  With Rohit, developed
        several FlatPred implementations for plus, times, negate etc.
        plus a basic left-to-right, deterministic-only evaluation engine.
      </action>
      <action dev="MarkU, Rohit" type="add">
        Translated the 500+ Jaza tests into standard Z conjectures and 
        wrote a JUnit harness which calls evalPred on each one (but
        conjectures of the form E=undefnum pass E to evalExpr and expect
        an exception to be raised).
        The resulting 'usertests' give a good measure of how much 
        progress we are making towards a useful animator.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
