<?xml version="1.0"?>
<status>

  <developers>
    <person name="Petra Malik" email="PetraMalik@sourceforge.net" id="Petra"/>
    <person name="Tim Miller" email="timmiller@sourceforge.net" id="Tim"/>
    <person name="Mark Utting" id="Mark"/>
  </developers>

  <changes>
    <!-- Add new releases here
         Some action types have associated images. By default, images are
         defined for 'add', 'fix', 'remove', 'update' and 'hack'. If you add
         src/documentation/resources/images/<foo>.jpg images, these will
         automatically be used for entries of type <foo>.
         Sample action:
         <action dev="JB" type="fix" due-to="Joe Contributor"
           due-to-email="joec@apache.org" fixes-bug="123">
           Fixed a bug in the Foo class.
         </action>
    -->
    <release version="0.2" date="unreleased">
      <action dev="Petra" type="add">
        Add LocAnn to (AST) terms created in the parser
        so that other tools can identify the position of the term.
      </action>
      <action dev="Petra" type="add">
        Parse latex markup directives (%%Zchar etc.) and add it into
        the AST.
      </action>
      <action dev="Petra" type="fix">
        Improve the operator table so that the rules from Section 8.3
        of the Z standard are followed.  This includes checks that
        a whole operator name is never defined more than once,
        that operators with the same precedence also have the same
        associativity, etc.
      </action>
      <action dev="Petra" type="fix">
        Improve error messages in case a parse error occured
        (compute correct line and column number).
      </action>
      <action dev="Mark, Petra" type="fix">
        Fix the computation of the name of a prefix function like,
        for instance, cardinality.
        Now, the parser does not add a leading space to the name of
        a prefix functions any more.  This closes bug #937623.
      </action>
      <action dev="Petra" type="fix">
        Write XML files using UTF-8 encoding instead of using the
        locale encoding.  Now the files written when using the
        command line tools zed2zml and ozed2zml with the -out argument
        are in UTF-8.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1" date="April 8, 2004">
      <action dev="Tim, Petra" type="add" context="admin">
        Initial Release.
      </action>
    </release>
  </changes>

  <todo>
    <actions priority="high">
      <action context="code" dev="open">
        Implement a visitor that annotates an AST indicating where braces are
        needed to enforce the given priority.  This is needed by printers
        that walk over an AST and print one of the markup languages.
      </action>
      <action context="code" dev="open">
        Add rules to the parser to handle Yuan Fang's changes to the
        Object-Z schema (i.e. SelfExpr, PolyExpr, PromotedAttrExpr, and
        ContainmentExpr).
      </action>
    </actions>
    <actions priority="medium">
      <action context="code" dev="open">
        Fix the latex printer.  The current latex printer tries to avoid
        putting hard spaces everywhere by using information from the latex
        markup table.  For instance, there is no need to put hard spaces
        around the latex command
        <code>\varg</code>
        since it is defined to be an inword (via the '%%Zinword \varg \_'
        directive in the prelude), i.e. spaces are added before
        and after it when it is tranlated back into unicode.
        But this is true only in most cases.  For instance, when defining
        the function
        <code>\function \varg ^{ ~\varg~ }</code>,
        the hard spaces cannot be omited since the second
        <code>\varg</code>
        is enclosed in braces and no spaces are added when it is tranlated
        to unicode.  The current latex printer does not handle this case.
        The current workaround (to be able to print the prelude) is
        to not use
        <code>\varg</code>
        at all, but user defined operators that use braces may not be
        printed correcly.
      </action>
      <action context="code" dev="open">
        Develop an e-mail markup to unicode converter.  It should
        return Symbol objects so that it can be fitted into the CztReader.
      </action>
    </actions>
    <actions priority="low">
      <action context="docs" dev="open">
        Design a Parser logo.
      </action>
      <action context="code" dev="open">
        Improve the output of schema text so that it generates
	semicolons versus newlines 'correctly'.  Note that LET expressions
	can only contain semicolons, but other schema text can contain
	either.  The choice between semicolon and newline could be done via
        some heuristics, but to do it properly would require recording
        which was used in the input, which requires significant changes
	to the XML schema for Z.
      </action>
    </actions>
    <!-- Add todo items. @context is an arbitrary string. Eg:
    <actions priority="high">
      <action context="code" dev="SN">
      </action>
    </actions>
    <actions priority="medium">
      <action context="docs" dev="open">
      </action>
    </actions>
    -->
  </todo>
</status>
