<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
  <properties> 
    <title>Welcome to CZT</title> 
  </properties>
  <body> 
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>The Community Z Tools (CZT) project is building a set of tools
        for editing, typechecking and animating formal specifications
        written in the <a href="http://www.zuser.org/z/">
        Z specification language</a>, with some support for Z extensions
	such as Object-Z, Circus, and TCOZ.
        These tools are all built using the CZT Java framework for Z tools.
      </p>
      <p>
        Beta-versions of the end-user CZT tools are now included in the
        CZT releases (download
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=86250">sources</a> or
        <a href="http://www.cs.waikato.ac.nz/~petra/">binaries</a>).
        This includes a
        <a href="http://www.jedit.org">jEdit</a>-based
        Z editor that gives WYSIWYG editing of the Unicode markup for Z,
        template-based insertion of Z constructs for LaTeX and Unicode
        markup, automatic typechecking on each save, a SideKick panel that
        shows the structure of your Z specification, conversion between
        the different markups and much much more.
        More information can be found in the
        <a href="manual.html">manual.</a>.
        Here is a screenshot, showing some random Z in Unicode format:
      </p>	
      <img src="images/jedit_unicode_example.png" 
                alt="CZT Tools within JEdit"/>
    </section>
    <section name="Background">
        <p>[Adapted from Andrew Martin's 
          <a href="http://web.comlab.ox.ac.uk/oucl/work/andrew.martin/CZT/proposal.html">original CZT proposal</a>]
	  The Z specification language was adopted as an ISO standard in 2002.
          It can be used to precisely specify the requirements or behaviour of
          systems, and analyze that behaviour via proof, animation,
          test generation etc.  However, one of the biggest barriers to the
          widespread use of the Z specification language seems to be the issue
          of tool support.
        </p>
        <p>Many projects have constructed Z tools, some of product quality,
          most as student projects. Few of them are integrated with each other;
          few support all the new ISO standard; fewer still build together
          to form the kind of integrated environment that developers are
          beginning to expect. Many good ideas have been developed to
          prototype stage, and then have been lost as projects have
          finished and students or researchers have moved on.  The number
          of times a request for a Z parser arises in the Z newsgroup
          suggests lots of people are producing tools, most of which will
          never be seen outside their own institute. An integrated effort
          will move forward the state of tools, and thereby the take-up of
          Z. 
        </p>
    </section>
    <section name="CZT Objectives">
      <p>Our objectives are to encourage interchange between existing Z
         tools (via a standard XML interchange format for Z),
         and to provide open-source libraries for building and integrating
         new Z tools.
         The software we are building includes:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>An <a href="zml/index.html">XML Schema markup</a> for Z.
            See the <a href="ext:zb-2003">ZB2003</a>
            proceedings for a paper describing this markup.</li>
        <li><a href="corejava/apidocs/">Java
            classes</a> for Z annotated syntax trees (AST).</li>
        <li>Java classes for converting between XML and Java AST.</li>
        <li>Java libraries for the common operations needed in every Z tool
            (markup-converters, parser, type-checker, etc.).
            A <a href="http://www.springerlink.com/index/10.1007/11415787_5">paper</a>
            describing these has been presented at 
	    <a href="http://www.zb2005.org">ZB2005</a>.
	    </li>
        <li>One or more simple graphical Z editors, with facilities for
            easily entering the special Z unicode symbols.  Initially we
            are using <a href="http://www.jedit.org">jEdit</a>.</li>
        <li>A Z animation tool called ZLive, with a customisable 
            graphical user interface.</li> 
        <li>Export tools, to output Z in other notations or for other Z tools.
            (example, HTML output, LaTeX output, translation to B and
            JML).</li> 
        <li>Extended versions of the libraries and tools to support Z 
            extensions such as
            <a href="http://www.itee.uq.edu.au/~smith/objectz.html">Object-Z</a>,
            <a href="http://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~dongjs/tcoz.html">TCOZ</a>,
            and <a href="http://www.cs.york.ac.uk/circus/">CIRCUS</a>.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
